so to me that's always if you learn
where you can save a ton of time and
where you can waste time and and you
become better and better mastering that
tool set I think that will make a really
big difference in what we see as a
really strong developer in the future
when you're building these tools you
want people to just start and play
around you don't want them to first like
log into a whole bunch of different
services and then they can do something
right so anything we can do to reduce
that friction and make sure that the AI
can have its own account in a way and
just work
there you're listening to the AI native
Dev brought to you by
[Music]
Tesla hello everyone welcome back to the
AI native Dev podcast uh today we're
going to talk about Ai and the web and
where is it headed and how to deal with
that and to help us explore all of that
world and more we have Matt bilman who
is the CEO and co-founder of netfi Matt
welcome to the show thanks for coming on
thank you thanks for having me so Matt
we're gonna talk a lot about web and AI
but looking at your background I
realized that you started your LinkedIn
profile in two years of being a music
editor in those and so I'm going to
start by asking you a totally different
question which is what's your view on AI
in music generation you're a fan you're
Pro you're against in all of the
creative Fields right I think it's just
going to be a new tool in our tool books
to be creative with I think when people
look at Ai and music a lot of them are
are thinking of like the low hanging or
AI can generate music that sounds just
like the music that we've been listening
to for for a while now and that's that's
cool there's probably like a lot of fun
use cases for that right but I think
more interesting with these things is
what are like creative artists going to
do with what you can do with AI that was
impossible to compose and come up with
or put together before you had this
capacity of maybe generating things with
a level of complexity or a level of who
knows right that you just couldn't do
before and again I probably wouldn't be
doing what I'm doing if I wasn't
generally a fan of technology and the
possibilities it opens up to just so
many other changes in music from the
invention of the musical notation
technology that really changed what
people even thought was music before it
was always just tied to something that
existed in a moment then the invention
of the gramophone again completely
changed what people even thought about
as music because before that like the
actual Sound of Music was something Epal
that only existed in the moment and so
suddenly just recording it really
changed like completely what people
thought of at music and and again very
early on you would just record classical
western music right I can put that out
but then so much of what people listen
to and think of this is music to them
today started because you could record
music and could spread it that's that
right and then that digital recording
came around and suddenly you had samples
right like and the beginning at that
time there was a lot of the similar
thoughts that around like AI right oh
it's like stealing other people's music
and so what is this going to music if
you're not drumming then you really done
it but really you can get electric
guitar or a drum or whatever it is that
you want and now I think it's just
accepted that of course like all of
these digital like sampling and so on is
a part of what you can do with music and
I think we're in the same stage with AI
right now that's the first geni for
making music that sounds mostly like a
fairly Bland version of of Music we've
already heard before but I'm sure that
the creative artists will come up with
really interesting things to do with
that technology that will probably again
change the the music we listen to a lot
that's be really fun to to follow love
that answer I'm I'm totally a fan of
that as well and I think a lot about the
dynamic Music Creation what happens when
UI doesn't just replace the human
Creator but rather augments the human
Creator by being able to create great
things so I think anyway I had to do it
like I was surprised I knew a lot about
your background you know the years of
founding netlify we we've known each
other for for quite a few years but I
didn't know that piece so I have to
start with that question but let's maybe
switch gears it is it does have Dev in
the title of this podcast
so we should probably dig a bit more
into the dev piece so there's a lot to
talk about when it comes to Ai and the
web and website building and
applications and and so much more maybe
I'll start with just what sort of seems
to be the most kind of ey candy type of
functionality that seems around Ai and
the web and that's these sort of AI
website Builders I'll tell you the
description and a website will come up
you see players like verell and weeks
and Shopify and like a bunch of these
others give us versions there's like
gazillion startups that are offering
this how do you think you've seen those
what's your opinion about these website
builders that are AI generated versus
not actually probably very similar to
your question about music right like I
think again the first step is that we
get a lot of these like gen builders
that can make websites that looks like
all the other websites we've built
before and and make them really fast but
maybe also fairly Bland right like yeah
the bad version of some pop song that
might have existed precisely and that's
probably like one of the first use cases
and there are a lot of good use cases
both in music and here right like maybe
you need some music for your podcast and
you can't afford to pay some artists for
royalties or something but you can get
something right and can help you create
right like maybe you need to like at the
lower end of the market there's always
been this very Rich landscape of wakes
and weely and square space and all all
of these like side Builders over time
right that are really valuable for you
want to open a popup restaurant and so
on right and you definitely don't have a
team of web developers going and
building something custom for you right
the first use of of these side Builders
will these be really useful in that
space But then similar to with music I
think the more interesting uses and more
decomposed form of it where it's not
like the AI just spitting out at at all
side but where it's more about how
developers actually orent their own
skill set with AI right and how does it
allow us to to build more and to build
more complex things and build them
faster right on the one hand when we
think about that space for netfi right
like we think of these AI building for
the web as a new kind of user of nlii
right that's no longer like a human
developer but an AI developer a while
ago we launched the nlii gbt that you
can like use from anywhere within the
sort of jat gbt landscape to just like
add mention nlii and you can now publish
whatever you did to the web and just
from that one we seeing more than a
thousand websites getting published to
notify every day these are like a
thousand websites a day that get
generated by Ai and I guess those are
probably not they're not your rock
ballads that sort of stay for decades
they're a different no they're
definitely often more epimeral or like
you start some little prototype and you
get it out or something right or someone
making a website for their girlfriend or
whatever like it's like a lot of that
kind of stuff and similarly we have some
of these more complex Site Builders like
b. new or GPT engineer or Devin also
using nlii API to make NY like the
default way if you ask it to build an
app right like it builds an app on nfy
and publishes it there from those and
other set of thousands of sites created
every day now on nfy right so AI are
becoming a pretty big user base a way
that's really interesting right and
that's one side of it but then the other
side of it is the whole landscape of
tools that are more granular in a part
of like sometimes connect as
collaborators to developers or there's
like tools like Cody a cursor or copilot
and so on that all helps developers
build faster and so on and I think the
higher up in the landscape of of use
cases and budgets and projects like the
more you shift away from some like
magical prompt that's click a button and
or make a prompt and it builds something
for you that you have little control
over and into like teams of develop ERS
being augmented with all kinds of AI
tooling the potential of what they can
do yeah that makes sense to me I think
aligned with with what I'm seeing which
is there's the bootstrap exercise and
there defense like a lot of these tools
also represent themselves that way of is
this the initial version of what would
be used I guess for that purpose it's
almost like a design and maybe content
layout type problem and it's a good
point that you make that these Builders
also tackle the underlying okay but how
do you actually make this thing live on
web and all that ntif being a perfect
example for that so many of them you see
them Deploy on the other side and I
would bet like a large percentage of
them probably resort to that because
they look for the known patterns that
are well documented tried and true and
also somewhat sufficiently opinionated
that they route them through some path
is well trotted because there's less
options around them and so they probably
have higher success with rifi and you
want them to set up something that
doesn't require imagine they just buil
you like a kubernetes cluster and AWS
running your site and then they're like
good
luck we need to figure that out that
would probably to yeah hold than faction
finish I I I think that's a really
interesting point which is AI to an
extent is the laziest developer in some
ways it is actually like a very invested
developer that might if you give it the
instructions it would not skip writing
documentation or creating test or it it
would do them to varying levels of
success but it would do all those steps
if instructed because it's obedient
uh but at the same time it looks for
things that are well trotted because at
least if it wants to be useful it seeks
the sort of low maintenance type
surrounding and so it makes the ease of
use that Dev tools aspire to anyway to
be able to reach a lot of developers
actually very applicable to AI as well
because instructing AI or instructing
llms is actually not that different than
instructing developers and M except that
developers might not be obedient follow
the instructions that you tell them of
course I C Jo in a company in Spain
where we built websites for small to
medium businesses we had a bunch of
other things going on the key sort of
money driver was building websit for
small to medium businesses at a very
large scale so at our Peak we were
building more than 100 websites a week
to give you a sense of the scale right
and had built this whole platform that
did like initial brief assigned the
freelance designer to the project took
you to iterations got it like to our
platform with content management and
design tooling and everything thing and
took it live and so on but a big part in
that process when working with like SNB
Sy things I wanted at a website would
definitely be to not be obedient and I
guess kind of the LMS are tricky in
their desire to please a little bit I
think you're hard press to so these
website Builders are today good examples
of just generating a repetitive song of
it but I guess for that purpose would
you say they're being effective it
sounds like they're definitely getting a
lot of usage on the netlify platform so
if we assume nlii is a a decent rep
presentation probably is of the number
of these websites that that get created
is that thousand number like quickly
growing was it 100 a year ago and now
it's a thousand a growing number Ultra
the number of of tools plugging into us
just goes off right so we definitely
seeing more and more through put there
right like I still think again that a
lot of it is like very ephemeral and so
on right like it still nugs so much
building real projects building
something that people might actually
take over and work on and keep building
and so on like that's been pretty cool
to see and even from Jet tvt right like
we've started to see like real
conversion flows where people start
there and then actually sign up for
notify with corporate email and start
doing things on the other side so
there's definitely some of the things
there that are starting to work my
senses again it's a mixture of the very
low end of the market and and then also
just stuff where you would never build
something before right I have an example
myself right like with my 18 month old
daughter when sit with laptop she she'll
come over and she'll laptop and she
wants something to to do with it and she
likes looking at some of the lits and
numbers that she recognizes and so on I
just has thought to build a little game
for her where it just full screen
doesn't do anything but when you press a
letter it will show that letter with a
fun animation right and now she'll come
and like press letters and see them spin
around and so on be excited and I
definitely probably wouldn't have
written a web app to do this right but
it was easy enough to just ask for
Stills like hey built this app right
people have a tendency to think that
there's like constant number of this
type of websites that the world needs
and now ai is going to come and build
this set up them and that's just not how
it works like you make it easier to do
custom development and suddenly you
start custom developing things that you
would just never have spent that time on
before that would never have been
created or automated yeah I love that
example and I hope your daughter enjoyed
that yeah and I think as they get better
yeah they don't need to be robust they
don't need to be comprehensive they just
need to be Mass easy to create and then
if they work often enough they still
need to work there it needs to be if
you're always failing you're not going
to do it again so I guess maybe let's
take a step back a little bit we already
talked a little bit about the the fact
that you have this new breed of users in
nlii which is these AI users uh but
maybe taking you level up how do you
think about AI in NY I have four
categories to think about like the the
first one is really like how do we use
AI internally attify to be more
effective and to build faster and better
and to how do we make nifi product
better by applying AI right what are the
opportunities that AI gives us to build
a bit of product and the third one is
really like how does our users and
customers build AI powered applications
with netlify and what does that change
in terms of the C Primitives we need to
offers is work close we need to offer
and then the f one is really this
category of like how AI going to use
netify and how can we make sure that
ntif is like the best deployment
platform for AI I love that sort of
fourth one and we touched on it but it's
probably worthy of more information but
let's maybe go through the other three
first I think the fourth one is probably
going to be helpful to inform the
conversation a little bit around it so
let's go through those I love that
breakdown of the four items so the first
one was how do you use AI uh to make
netify I guess a better organization on
it we're talking a little bit more about
development over here so there examples
of ways in which you use AI in
development that you try it out and you
realize they do or they don't yeah
obviously we're using a in many
different parts right but we've also
really tried to see with these Builders
and so on how much code can iI write for
us right and I've tried to also
internally push our developers like on
make sure you go try to augment yourself
with AI because there are really
powerful pieces there right like I've
spent time trying to build some medify
features and just sit down and see with
these different tools how much help
would they give me right like I made my
own conclusions there but also just
really encourage the the team to use
them and I think there's the individual
developer tool choice where a lot of
them are using co-pilot in different
ways right but it's also like less
integrated tooling like just cat DBT and
CLA in in their own as tools and all of
these faces of it right that's a little
less ordained by us as a company and
more like encourage like you got to
figure out what works and share with the
team and then there are some of the
tools we've evaluated are there more
programmatic things we can do to our
code bases where can be like developers
in different ways and we've tried
different code generating systems some
of the ones that have tried to tap into
a get up issue and try to solve it and
still find ticket automatically or
something yeah and I still find that
that level like the models right now
still not at a place where that really
makes sense right or where they can
participate they don't succeed at a
reasonable level to be worth the the
noise so like they're not a good enough
developer that you really want them in
your code base right if you have a not
that good developer and they write a on
of poll requests but you have to like
thoroughly review all of them and some
of them might have big mistakes in them
and so then it's not necessarily at a
time saer right like it might just a
distraction I love that phrasing of
they're just not good enough developers
that you want them in your code B that
but for the coding assistance you don't
find at least not in mass that it's a
problem that people are checking in
inferior code compared to what they did
before like you feel like your
developers are managing to supervise it
sufficiently that you don't see this as
a repeating pattern yeah yeah and it I
think also because we have a strong code
riving culture internally right so I
think the peer accountability there is
pretty strong right if you suddenly
start making a bunch of bad polar CIS
like your PS reviewing why you're doing
this as long as you have strong
engineering culture there I I I think
good developers will not suddenly become
bad developers like they'll just get
more productive developers right so
that's very much something I'm
encouraging I love that accountability
be off it because fundamentally the more
guard rails you have the faster you can
run because you have the confidence that
that you're not going to sleep and and
that also incentivizes the behavior that
the developers will you have you have
two effects here one is culturally the
developers know that their code will be
reviewed and so maybe they themselves
are more responsible but then two is you
actually have the code review process to
identify so I love how sometimes the use
of AI highlights the importance of
practice we've already perceived to be
good practices so it's a great and I
think it's going to be an interesting
piece that I think it can make a big
difference to a good developer how good
they become at Ai and that will be a
pretty big differentiate I think in a
developer right because I think it's
very much something you need to learn
how to use and apply for it to not be
like autocomplete of GitHub is often I
both see it in myself and I hear it from
a lot of like more senior developers
that they turn that off because it's
just I don't know again it's like care
programming with a developer that's
several levels below you and it's like
constantly okay let's do this
differently the suit and it's like noisy
and so on but on the other hand sort of
intentional pront being for code can
really speed up some of like things that
would otherwise take really long like
when I first was were doing this I was
trying to see could I get GPT 4 to do
some code changes on our plot in for
traffic server which is like big C++
open source code base right and anything
more can you implement this or something
it it would just hallucinate all kinds
of apis that didn't exist and so on
right like it completely useless but on
the other hand telling it something like
I need a function that takes betterer
object and then extract these specific
values and then compar like the accept
language string split it up into a
format that you can work with and then
compare it with the actual like setting
of a redirect Rule and then return a
conclusion of like when I could give it
like a really take this input do this
thing and give this output right like it
would just completely correctly write
that function in 30 seconds right if
anyone has been doing that in C+ right
like that level of string comparison and
manipulation and so on that would have
taken me a long time to like to you just
remember all of those like standard
Library functions and figure out the
right way to do it in the memory Safe
Way and so on right I can just wrot it
in one go so to me there always if you
learn where you can save a ton of time
and where you can waste time and and you
become better and better at mastering
that tool set I think that will make a
really big difference in what we see as
a really strong developer in the future
yeah yeah I fully agree and it's
interesting to think about these things
as specifications versus as prompts Al I
guess these are still prompts and it's
about prompt engineering to try and see
how do you guide the system I guess on
one hand you expect the llms to get
better at needing less instruction and
describing what you want but what what
people forget or or underappreciate is
that you do need to tell the LM what it
is that you want to do it can't read
your mind if you just compare whatever
the accept language header to one of the
western languages maybe it defines a
western language in a different one to
the one that you want so sometimes you
do need to get a little bit more
specific as a human might as one of your
developers on the team if you give them
the instructions and you also mentioned
though that you make good use of code
mod which I found interesting do you
want to tell us a little bit about that
yeah like we've done evaluations of a
bunch of different tools and the one way
I should be working with is cod.com
we're basically using it to do with code
based migrations so in our in main app
for example app. ny.com traditional
react app started a long time ago right
like back in the start of 2016 or so on
right like and one of the components
that were pretty out of date was the
react router and it's like react router
has changed a lot from like the early
days to now and those changes are pretty
goes pretty deep through the whole code
basee and at the same time like being
stuck on an old version with was holding
back a lot of other upgrades of react
dependencies and so on so that was one
of the big projects that we use cod mod
to to do like and code mod is a is a
defined like by itself it is a
deterministic manipulation of code to
yeah so code need to go from version one
to version two or from the idea with the
tool is just taken on the basic idea
that you can write Cod marks that that
doesn't look at the that are not find
and replace in text right but that look
looks at the abstract syntax tree of
your code and then can apply
transformations to that abstract syntax
tree right like a lot of these kind of
migrations can then be expressed as a
set of code mods right because again if
you try to do it with search and replace
that's just not going to work right but
there is a set of like code mods that
can express how do you go from how the
router worked in this place to how it's
supposed to work in this place right
like now the challenge is that writing
like transformations of abstract syntax
trees
that's
not can come along and
start and so that's where what G mod is
is really helping us get the AI to
Define and iterate and test on those
code mods so once those are in place
then based on that their system would
essentially like apply that throughout
the code base and make some pretty nly
big p requests that we didn't have to
run a lot of testing on to make sure it
works and so on but that has actually
really allowed us to run through that
whole series of updates to react router
and then the react versions that were
behind because of that dependency and so
on so that's actually some pretty big in
terms of lines of code and pretty
massive contributions to our code based
that's come in that path through AI but
but with have a lot of human in the loop
sty style very attended process of it
yeah I like that analogy because I do
think there is a pattern that you see in
places in which if you ask AI to
generate something that is a more
constrained space it can do a better job
actually in the world of web there's
also wasp introduced this thing called
Mage which is a GPT generator actually
you just described Amplified GPT and so
if you're giving the llms instructions
of something that is a much more small
well-defined space it might still be
complicated but there are less options
around it there aren't 177,000 ways to
do a loop there aren't also like things
are much more contained that it
generally can do a pretty good job and
so this pattern of having the llm
generate something that is that confined
space because that's really what you
want and then applying that to code
since the gor I've seen it in the devops
space seen it in WASP so it's really
interesting to see how it applies to
code mode is this something you you
built in house or is this code mode the
code mode itself is an open project I
think originally created in Facebook it
was before
meta around it yeah precisely Alex there
was a PM on that product at Facebook or
that there right like he he's buil
kmart.com around it and yeah and have
both like this registry of Open Source
code mods that you can apply if you like
you're starting to work with teams like
the react team or the remix teams to
just like when they launch a new version
and they have a set of code mods that
you can just go apply to your code base
and upgrade it and that's really
interesting right full dis closure I'm
ultra small invest now in the company
but also because I think it's really
interesting because those kind of
version upgrades over time it's a
challenge of our whole ecosystem right
like that all of these versions keeps
changing and either you can waste a lot
of developer time like chasing them and
on the other hand if you don't do that
suddenly you run into these moments
where you're now blocked because you're
like pretty far behind and getting
really up to date is now like some
massive lift right but you might not be
able to add like a new dependency or
something before you've lifted up those
old dependencies so I think yeah if if
we can build tooling that can really
help like systematically helping on that
like just dependency migration problem
that's really valuable right that's
really a lot of good insights about
using to make nei's own development more
productive guess the next point you made
was around the of using AI to make neifi
products better maybe actually before we
go there can you give us just for the
users who are not as familiar with nii
give us just a couple of minutes on what
netify is and what you have just to
contextualize theuse in it yeah so neifi
is a web development platform for the
web really based on like their original
Insight was that if you really decoupled
your architecture so you thought about
all of your backend business lot you can
apis and systems just has a set of apis
and then thought off the actual web user
experience as like a self-standing
application then we could really deliver
like a a unified platform that takes
care of all the Automation and operation
that you need to make sure that the code
your developers right gets in front of
actual customers on a domain in
production as fast as possible and with
high performance and high high rate
right so we integrate all the release
management the cicd and like they're
setting up staging environments for
every single poll request and like
giving you collaborative tools on top of
that even giving you tools for for
non-developers to be part of the process
and give feedback into poll requests or
do visual editing even on on top of the
website and so on with the actual
operation of the infrastructure right so
we operate a large Global Network and
with with everything you would expect
there like web application firewall he
does mitigation we have like Edge
compute and serverless compute for both
sort of like the The Edge rendering you
might need for modern Frameworks or for
personalization and for all the back end
for front end you'll need to actually
talk to all of these different apis and
build on top of them really just with
the goal of helping web teams avoid
spending their time on all the
Automation and operation that sits after
they write their code and content and
focus on like actually like creating the
coding content that makes a difference
and then we'll take it from there and
help them ship faster and better results
and and I think very powerful platform
and and I think one of its distinctions
as well compared to maybe other players
in the space which is it is quite you
already use I think the words composable
earlier on which is it's opinionated it
has those paths and it off flows them
but you can say I'm going to use this
piece of the platform over here I'm
going to plug into something else and
here there might be like seven different
ways in which I yeah publish the content
or I write content or five cmss that I
integrate with different apps and you
create those so this composability
modularity of the of the system is a is
a COR strength of it right it's is
relevant I think to some of your the AI
features that you've been us you've been
discussing so thanks for that sort of
primer I guess inde take us into that
world so how do you use AI to make the
ntif effect products better yeah so our
philosophy is really like that that we
don't go into the space of using AI to
help write your code or write your
content or everything like that right
like in our world that's what is like
outside the worldall of nfy right but we
help you take that stuff live faster so
we're constantly thinking about like how
can AI help one those reduce the
friction from when you write the code or
when you write the content to having it
on a Ulin production one of the first
sort of like public features we launched
there explicitly was the why did it fail
Buton just based on the fact that one of
the most common friction is like you
written some code you now push it to a
full request on GitHub we run the build
for that code but instead of going live
the build fails and now you get like ah
it failed I got to jump into NFI I got
to look at all the logs got to try to
figure out like what happened and what
should I do about it right so there we
put a a button in the UI that that you
can click that it why did fail and when
you click that will take the context of
the build and the build log and so on
pass it for an LM and try to answer like
why did this fail and give you Al a
proposed solution what that's what yeah
very practical kind of sifting through
data but with a cal eye that now lm's
enabled to understand what happened and
saving me a lot of time in the process
yeah and we launched that sometime in
May this year and and since then we've
had more than a 100 built debucks by
that button that's 25,000 developer
hours sa since then or something and do
you know like the accuracy rate of it of
those 150,000 times like how often did
it get it right versus wrong I I wish I
had B numbers there right like it's a
little harder for us to instrument if
even to know again because it's not like
we also have a box and to say implement
the fix right like it is still like
giving you the advice and how to fix it
and why did it fail so that's not like a
sure fos to measure did they take that
advice or did they do something else
yeah but these are developers so if you
get it wrong very often they will tell
you they will tell us and quite the
contrary we've even seen that internally
just when we started in it private BS
our own team started using it a lot as
all of these it definitely sometimes
gets it wrong right but there's also
just a la of times where it just saves
you like in some cases it might even be
something that's fairly obvious but you
get like a a large build output log with
error messages and so on and you got to
just situate yourself and figure it out
and you just click that button that just
immediately I identified it it's like a
very nice feeling yeah yeah yeah no
that's a lot of time Sav so that one is
like a very concrete immediate the
practicality of it yeah and feels very
applicable to other systems those
building so systems around precisely
said also like our call philosophy of
how do we think about Ai and AAL set
right like ideally not writing from
second like you can do that other places
ideally we should have everything wired
off so we can have Vis do things that
just that doesn't add complexity to your
workflow but just like speeds up how you
work yeah and the next feature we just
launched here at composed that's in
private BS and now is what we call EI
assistant publishing and it ties into we
are obviously like very much a developer
First Tool right and we're really meant
for teams that that want to apply to Vel
opers to build web experiences but we've
always had this Vision that like those
developers have a set of stakeholders
that are not developers that I call part
of that web team right being marketeers
that write the actual like copy and
content and messaging that needs to go
live the signers that work with them on
the assets and so on and we only really
succeed for our customers if we can help
those developers help the full team
right and we can make the full path
faster and when we look at a lot of the
the web project you will have code and
templates and then typically you will
always have some content infrastructure
behind it right like typically like
hitless cms's maybe you sometimes you
even have a couple you have a hitless
CMS and you have an e-commerce platform
a sometimes you have a legacy CMS and
like modern Hitler CMS and all sort of
combinations it's like technology never
you layer on something new but you never
actually remove the old but the key is
that for developers to make effective
use of content they need that content to
be in a structured varable format and
and that's like ideally in some Modern h
l is with with great content in right
like now in our experience even
internally at neifi none of the creators
and marketeers and so on ever do their
creative work in structured content they
always seems to work in at neifi they
work at Google Docs and option right any
anything will even developers right if
one of our developers a new block post
for our defa they don't write in yeah
it's hard to write you don't want to
write it in a form you want to write it
in some free form you just want to write
it free form so it's always just like
notion is typically where the developer
on gets written and the marketeers
typically write this in in Google ducks
right there just the split there like
similar to how one of the early things
we did at nlii was like realizing that
developers have this set of tools of
their code editor their local
development environment and GitHub where
they do their actual work and then
there's all this tooling after that for
getting it out into the world we early
unrealized we could just plug into
GitHub and just make sure that every
time the developer push to GitHub we run
a building we give them a URL when they
can see how it looks like we started
thinking about what would it look like
to expand this to these stakeholders at
work in Google doc and notion and so on
right like in this kind of the early
path towards that where we say if you
want to publish a new page whether it's
like a simple blog post or whether it's
like a product page that might have a
whole set of complex templates and so on
instead of like first writing all of
that up in Google docks and then
typically going and asking like a
developer or some Semite technical
person or something that who's just like
doing CMS entry or something go put this
into the CMS we can get the llm to do
that for you like just go to ntif visual
ining layer and just say start a new
page for from this document right and
then we use the lmm to take that
unstructured content and get it into the
structured format we already set in this
space where we can run the the full like
since we're the rendering infrastructure
and so on right like we can run the
preview for you can show how it actually
looks like and we can then give you the
visual editing on top of that to make
tweaks to anything like the L might have
gotten wrong or you want to change and
so I'm like straight on the page and
again just really aim to like can we
take that process sometimes even takes a
couple of days not like of intense work
but you got to find someone that has
time to put it into the CMS and then
they got to set it up and then they send
you back a link and then you have to
find the time to go verify that link and
then there's some iterations and so on
can we shorten that to just can we get
that down to just like a 15 minute
session and you're live right I think uh
that's what we're working on yeah yeah
really like that and I guess I think of
it as like an entry point to development
in platform so structure is basically
all the prud to Cod need structure can I
simplify that and I think aligned with
market trends that we're seeing with the
whiteboarding solutions with these
others in which you can describe
something in or loose form and can
evolve it into
structur great uses inside great uses in
the product thanks for describing all of
those we probably should talk a tiny bit
about how do customers build on AI
although here in the podcast we're
mostly focusing on how do you develop
applications with AI versus on top of AI
but maybe use a couple of words on that
and then a couple of words on that AI
user that we talked about before mostly
around what is it that you do to improve
acknowledging this as a user what is it
that yeah so in terms of obviously like
develop first building with nlii as as
AI just becomes a more and more key
building block of every user experience
we built it will be like more and more
integral to all developers that a lot of
the content or data or whatever they
they need might come from AI systems
right like for AI workflows so of course
we're thinking a lot about what does
that in this kind of gam architecture
with like front end and backend for the
front end and so on what are the new
premises that we might have to build or
how might our pret needs to evolve to
keep making sure that building on top of
these AIS are really great experience
right and that's been things we've
already done like making sure that all
of our originally nlii functions were
totally synchronous right like you would
send a request to the function and then
when it was done we send you a response
right like it became really important to
add streaming responses to functions
because right teally if you build on top
of gbt 4 or something you're not going
to get like an instant response said
going to get some stream of tokens that
you want to that takes long enough to
generate that you want to stream it back
to the user the experience is terrible
stream it in in the world of totally
right and and then you also start seeing
these more complex patterns where it
becomes more like agents and assistance
where it becomes less of okay send one
request to an llm and streaming back but
where it becomes more these types of
workflows right get some stuff from the
user now you got a trigger an initial
prompt with an LM that might give you
like a planning stage or something like
that and then you might even need to
spin up several different like processes
to do those different steps in parallel
and once all of those are done you can
update the end result but meanwhile as
they go you want to show updates to the
user and so on so we're thinking a lot
about how does that change what the code
you write for that little PL and and how
it can make it run and at compose when
we buil the AI assisted publishing
feature we ran into a lot of that
ourselves right and since we're building
it on NFI one of our principal Engineers
built this whole sort of workflow engine
on top of our normal servus Primitives
of scheduled functions and blob storage
and and serverless compute and so on so
we also packaged that up as an extension
for asynchronous workloads to again make
it really simple for for our users to
write those kind of workloads when
they're dealing with VMS and I think
that's another wave forward that we're
just constantly thinking about right for
where we sit in the space What are the
tools that look different that might not
have been that important before but
that's becoming really important well
building these type of experiences and
it fits into the future is already here
but not evenly distributed it's you know
none of these are like entirely new
capabilities these are all things that
existed but they went from being an edge
case to being a a common case and so you
have to support them a bit more
inherently and I guess it's interesting
to think about the notion of an llm
interaction on your site being maybe as
prevalent as a database call I'm looking
a lot of things like local first
architectures for building web apps
again because those are more of an edge
case now for if you're building like
multiplayer experiences and so on but
again it's it's suddenly much more
normal that like in all of these
workflows and so on you have these
agents going up and doing stuff then
almost every web experience we build are
going to be a multiplayer experience the
other players are just not humans but
these agents doing stuff right but
architecturally it means that suddenly a
lot of those things that were like an
itch case in the the past could quickly
suddenly become a really common I need
to have this yeah very interesting to
think about how these use cases become
as prevalent as querying data or how do
they become common enough in
applications that are not deemed complex
the application in general but they now
have these Els so the three of the four
in each of those there's a lot to say
around the use of AI to accelerate
development in edify about how do you
use AI to make your own products better
about how do you build AI into a net
application I'm interested about that
fourth bit which frankly I didn't think
about that deeply until we've started
having the conversation ahead of this
episode which is all these AI users you
mentioned that are using netlify so we
already described a bunch of these tools
a bunch of these Builders already use
nlii by default what is it that you can
do as netlify to help promote that
generally it's a good thing you want
them to be able to successfully netlify
definitely want them to do that by
default if you're building a tool that
you want AI to use which is not the same
as building an AI tool what can you do
have you tried things that you've
already seen work better than others
when I built even the predecessor tredi
called bit balloon that was like the
first step into this like how do you
build these like decoupled front and the
first tagline way back then like in the
end of 2013 or something was back then
like hosting for the programmable web
right that got replaced pretty quickly
and so on but there was this idea of
like outside of uses building with nlii
nlii is also in itself kind of an apepi
with CLI in a tool set right like in
open API spe and so on like our app.
netlify.com is me it's just like a a
client side client on top of that our
CLS is another CLI is another client on
top of that right that kind of now just
turns out to be really useful things for
AI models wanting to interact with our
product right there like a clear this is
how you should use this as an AI the
other PA that like other things have
been this flow we again we lached that a
long time ago but that suddenly starting
to become more relevant that's like a
deploy now flame leader where you'll see
that flow very clearly if you try to
like both that new right and you go in
and ask it to build an app and you say
deploy and it'll just deploy to nlii it
won't ask you as an inducer at first
like you need to go authenticate with
nlii and so and it'll just deploy you
there but it will give you a link that
say if you actually want to do something
with this you can click through and you
can then claim the site and it'll get
added to your n account right so remove
the friction of saying do I have a
netlify account or do I precisely right
removing the friction from these AI
tools to just be the the user first and
then potentially hand what they build
over to a human in when you're building
these tools you want people to just
start and play around you don't want
them to first like log into a whole
bunch of different services and then
they can do something right so anything
we can do to reduce that friction and
make sure that the AI can have its own
account and a way and just work there
and then give it to a user when it's
done more like almost thinking a little
about some of these in a similar way if
we're thinking about like how
Freelancers and agencies need to use our
platform and what we need to build from
that right like these AI are kind of a
new kind of like team player like that
right and we got to think through what
does that mean for the flows of of how
you build with our app right so that's
both that programmatic aspect of
obviously if you don't have clearly CLI
or AP driven blow that is easy for these
AIS to tap into then they can't do much
right but then there's also this human
aspect of the flow right what the
registra look like and not just human so
it sounds like great docks which I guess
you minimally alluded to it's well
document about here that to begin with
very programmable with good examples of
it and then subsequently zero friction
on registration which actually feels
very important for llms because I think
for a user their owners of their email
to register for different accounts is
still friction but it's like relatively
low friction but I can definitely see
how for an AI system the fact that they
need to register they have no email but
has no no email on behalf of this user
and so the registration is a big deal
and removing that is significant all of
those are are great things I can see how
they make AI successful as users of
netlify are the things after you've
learned that AIS are using your system
but you've tried to change because all
of those are things where you I don't
want to say like you planned well or you
designed yourself correctly for the
programmable web are there things you've
tried since that successful I think
there more things that we're still
trying to work through for these
different providers right there for
example with Chad GPT like one one of
the flows we use when you publish there
is that if you don't claim the site we
treat it as Emeral and it's deleted
within an hour or something like that
right so to keep that but then there are
all of these systems where people still
don't want to claim but want to make it
like shable and so on so they don't want
it to go away and once we have that then
we need to start also working around all
the bad things that comes from that of
what happens when someone jumps into one
of these elements and ask them to me
something that looks like chase.com and
ask people to put in their credit card
right and how do we work on notifying
the user of the service that has the AI
that their user is doing bad things with
us and so on so again there's a lot of
these problems that are not as straight
up like
technical limitation
but then I think other pieces of it is
more of on the composable side right
because then there's again when these
tools want to build with one thing is
like the simpler examples now are just
pure front and depths and don't do
anything more more right but when they
also want both a front end and a
database somewhere else and like these
more plug together systems where
multiple partners come together and
there I think there's some things to
Think Through that's almost more like
how can we start standardizing on some
of these patterns across providers right
like how can we like other ways we can
use the open web to make it clear what
we allow an AI to do and and how we can
be used by by AIS as tools and there
ways we can make standards for how AIS
can compose those tools together I think
that's like the next Frontier in a lot
of this that will probably happen first
in proprietary wall Gardens right like
where inside you can name all the
different pieces that you can name all
the different pieces and they can all be
tied together but I think it's pretty
important if this is going to be a
really important way of building and and
and starting and so on it's going to be
really important that we find ways
centered around the open way to solve
these problems equally like ideally
probably as it always is right like in
forms that are probably a little more
clunky than in one world Garden but that
also fundamentally really open and
allows anyone to publish and participate
in this composable like economy of tools
that that can plug together and build
fre yeah and connect so that's a great
lead into indeed maybe using the last
sort of 10 minutes or so of our
conversation to talk about where this is
headed this has been great insights on
how you know significantly AI
interweaves into everything that you do
I think we would both agree that where
we're headed this is just getting
started this just the beginning so maybe
take out your crystal ball and and say
as as you think about your your world
this world of of the web maybe specific
a jamstack the composable web in 5 years
time in 10 years time maybe even further
what would you say are the primary
changes that you are anticipating the
reason that people start like thinking
about composable architecture in
opposition to buying some monolithic
tool for here's a monolith for building
your corporate.com or he is like a
monolith for building your e-commerce or
he is like all of those the reason
people start thinking about like
composable as a term and a category that
they want to adopt is on the one hand to
get flexibility and the experiences they
can build right like you want to be able
to apply custom development to build
some custom experience but you want to
be able to do it with fast time to
Market and without building the parts of
the experience that are not unique to
you right so if you're like a highend
luxury brand you want to build a very
tailored like web experience for your
e-commerce that represents that but you
don't necessarily want to build
e-commerce right like you don't want to
build like content storage for that so
you want to be able to take like
reusable components put them together
there and then build really fast on top
of them and you want to know that those
different components you pick you can
evolve them independently as the world
evolves and as different Alternatives
comes along where in the traditional
monol you got stuck with maybe some
areas it was best in class but there are
a lot of areas that it sucked and
couldn't do anything about that so
that's what motivates that shift and I
think the Big M market trends around AI
will accelerate the need for those like
for going composable right and that's
like the first reason for that is just a
lot of things are hard to predict around
AI but what's really easy to predict is
that it will accelerate everything right
like you'll get more content you'll get
more code you'll get more assets yeah a
natural reaction of of reducing as we've
touched on before the barrier of enter
the barrier uh of of the effort to
create so more will be created more of
everything right and that means faster
evolving tool sets and and again like
that just puts more pressure on sitting
on like some large monolith it also puts
more pressure and typically the roll out
processes that comes when like your UI
and your back end is tied together and
everything might be like more risky to
roll out and so on right so you need
systems that can do very high throughput
and very high flexibility and so on
right but then the other sort of more
major thing that I'm thinking through is
really
what I would call like UI 2.0 right like
where right now all of that acceleration
from AI we're just using it to build the
same user experiences that we built the
last decades faster right so we're not
really like doing anything massively new
but we're making the code and the asset
and the the signs and everything faster
right right that feels like just the
first step even tying back to that
opening question on on on music right
like the same right well just like make
the same pop songs but faster right like
and that that itself is a change because
as as we just said it would create more
content in places that couldn't be
created before just like it can create
music in places more maybe customization
and such faster pace of change but it's
still not New Creations it's just a
faster moving Beast which once again is
is another compounding you could say
devops has done that and cloud has done
that and Java has done that all these
things have JavaScript has done that
they keep compounding on the pace of
development in this case also content
creation as well totally so the peace
goes up but I think if we look broader
out into the next five to 10 years then
we'll see much more radical change right
like in the sense that gradually we'll
start figuring out like what kind of
user experiences is that we can build
when especially when the core
constraints that we've had on all human
computer interfaces since the first one
that's really like that computers can
just understand intent or something
right like you need very transactional
and and predictable interactions you
click a button the computer does a
predictable thing you type a command the
computer does what the command says
right like and that constraint is just
seeping away right like into you can
actually just it can understand intent
and go do a bunch of things right and
the only way we've really exploited that
yet is in like in chatbot interfaces
right that feels very primitive right
and I think that's a part that's the
most impossible to predict how it will
unfold but I think it's easy to predict
that it will unfold right that we'll
start seeing people come up with these
patterns of user experiences that you
could never have built without AI that
we just not possible right and we'll see
that even changing possibly the
landscape of the devices and the
hardware we used to interact with
computers with as those possibilities
change right and that will be really
fundamental like that I think will be as
bigger change to what you're supposed to
be building at on the web as mobile was
possibly even bigger and similar to
every other platform change that there
will be like lots like the actual stuff
you will need to build like it was
impossible to predict when the iPhone
came out like what are the things like
five years after that people will be
building as s right but in every one of
those platform changes there's also some
things that are very predictable right
and one of them is just like this
tension between closed platforms and
open platforms right where obviously
large players will have a strong
interest in this rep platforming being
proprietary platforms that they own and
control into with Gard that they can
monetize and then a lot of us will have
to try to fight for an open web
alternative to that that can still
deliver the kind of experiences that
users will suddenly start to expect
right so that whole cycle that's
happened with mobile and with social
media and with all those like think it's
it's just about to start really playing
out again I think that's going to be
like one of the key areas where we as
NFI really thinking about like for
developers how can we keep making the
web the right platform to to innovate
and build these new experiences on and
how can we keep the type of qualities
the web has around like like TS where
there's no gatekeeper and you can just
fire domain and and and build whatever
you want on that domain and put it in
front of people right like how can we
make those strengths really compelling
so we keep this like open shared
infastructure the best platform to build
from yeah no that's a really a stute
observation and and I agree that it's a
risk that we have to have to deal with
and I guess we're seeing it on all
layers of the llms all the way from at
the bottom the foundation models
themselves versus open weights versus
few that are open source properly but
then also further up indeed with if you
were to build an application even these
autonomous engineers and and such they
might be very compelling but what does
it mean for the development methodology
over here for most of them we don't know
the answer because they're still behind
a wall they're not publicly available
but the sentiment is that those are hey
you're going to commit to this platform
is going to be more the Microsoft of old
or the Borland uh type environment it
wouldn't necessarily be the open Java or
the subsequently JavaScript and open web
so it's interesting because I think
there's a good chance that in a closed
system you can produce Innovations
faster and create things that are
cohesive faster and they will probably
happen that will have an advantage but
we just need to not accept that as the
destination but rather as a stepping
stone Matt this has been excellent
conversation longer than most of our
conversations because there's just so
much to say thanks again for coming in
and and sharing these observations and
setting stuff on the nlii front
especially I I really love how the
investments in appealing to a broad
developer base have drawn in this new
coder this new creature thei but a lot
of other guidance as well so thanks for
coming on to the show thanks so much for
having me this was a lot of fun really
great conversation and thanks everybody
for tuning in and I hope join us for the
next
[Music]
[Applause]
one thanks for tuning in join us next
time on the AI native Dev brought to you
by Tesla